hi all welcome back again to our Tosca
playlist and today we are going to talk
about an interesting topic and it's all
about API testing so how do you do API
testing in Tosca now we have seen a lot
of examples about how we scan and
automate our web applications or even a
PDF document right so Tosca can automate
any type of application or it can scan
different types of applications based on
the engine right so Tosca has got all
these different engines through which it
can interact with this applications and
similarly it has got a API engine
through which it can interact with
different types of apis okay
and Tosca is not able to only send and
receive requests or even verify your
responses for your apis but it can also
scan your apis right obviously uh that
needs some level of documentation for
your apis basically like a Swagger
documentation if it is present then you
can scan that particular
documentation and all your API messages
will be created automatically by the API
scan
we'll look at an example but first let's
see how you can basically interact with
this API scan okay so in this API
testing uh tab when you go to this
particular tab you will find the API
scan and to launch this application you
need to start API scan
so this will basically open a new window
it is like a separate tool in itself
which has got a lot of lot of different
options okay and you can send and
receive requests and responses you can
do all types of things which any other
API testing tool will provide you okay
but the most interesting uh option is
scanning you can scan a particular file
or you can scan a particular URI which
is basically a
the URL for your API okay and as you can
see there are different formats which
you can scan but we'll talk about it
little bit later
first I want to show you that there are
two ways of opening this particular
window or particular tool which is the
Tosca API scan so one way which I have
already shown you through Tosca
Commander but now if I go ahead and
close my Tosca Commander there is a
second way of launching API scan even if
there is no Tosca commander on your
machine okay so how you can do that
go to your search bar and search for API
scan
once you search for the API scan you can
see the API scan application and I can
run it independently without posca
Commander you can see uh I don't have
toss the commander running in the
background
so when I open uh you will see the same
window opening with all the same
features and how you work everything
remains same
but the biggest difference between how
you launch API scan from Tosca commander
and how you launch it from your desktop
is this particular API scan application
it doesn't require any particular
license okay so you can run it
independently and freely without
requiring a license but obviously if you
want to integrate your API testing with
your web application testing and you
want to uh do more uh with your API test
then obviously you will require Tosca
Commander but for just checking your
apis whether your request and response
is working
um or some aspects of your apis are are
working correctly or they have been
designed correctly they have been
developed correctly so that you can
basically do with this particular
application
and it also provides you with the
facility to scan uh which we already
talked about so this can be used uh
along with other developers or your uh
API Architects or designers right and
you can sit with them and you can also
provide this tool to them they don't
need to install Tosca Commander or they
don't need a license they can just open
this API scan and they can play around
with their own apis to basically do some
initial testing or to check whether
their apis are ready for testing okay
the other Advantage is as I said uh for
doing more with your API testing you
require the Tosca commander and to do
that we need to basically export
whatever we have created here uh into
our Tasker Commander now there are two
ways of it one way if we are opening it
right from your desktop you need to uh
export the API test case uh and that
will be created as a subset which again
you need to import back into Tosca
Commander right
but if you have opened this from the
Tosca Commander then it will be directly
integrated which means the folders will
be automatically created for you you
don't need to import anything or export
anything it will be directly uh taking
you to the Tosca Commander API testing
window okay
so that's the only major difference
apart from the licensing part but a rest
of the functionality as I said Remains
the Same right
now let's talk about the basic
functionality uh without looking at the
scanning functionality so the basic
functionality of any API testing tool is
uh it is the ability of that particular
tool to send any request and receive any
response right so you can view that
response uh in right in this tool and
you can also verify how much time it
took uh what are the response values
which you are expecting if you want to
send some Header information if it
includes some parameters like path
parameters so everything can be done
right from here okay
so let's see what are the different
options and also let's try to send a
simple request and then we can see how
it works in the API scan okay
so for this example I'm going to use
this particular API
it is just a demo API which basically
returns
um a page which all the list of users
for this particular get request
obviously there are lots of other
requests which you can send but I'll be
using this you can see this is the
request
resource or along with the URL and this
is the response okay so it will return
me this particular response with all the
different user details okay
to send any particular request in your
API scan you need to First create a
message right
so first you can see a default D
structure which is already also present
on the left hand side this is its own t
structure when I can create any number
of messages or folders okay so our
folder is already created you can see I
can also rename this particular project
okay and I can create my own messages
here so these are basically the API
messages and once I create this message
uh maybe I can call it I can rename it
to get request
okay or get a list of users
and then I need to select a method now
if you are familiar with API rest API
methods then these are all the methods
which are available in the rest API and
the most useful ones or the most
frequently used ones are get post put
delete right but there are that's also
if you want to use them
for me currently it is the get method I
need to provide a endpoint and a
resource these are the two most
important information which you need to
provide with any API request okay
and then you can also provide the
payload but for a get request you don't
require a payload for that will be
required for a post request okay
and then as I said you can also provide
parameters uh and parameters out of
three types here first is the query
parameters then second is path and then
you can also use header parameter okay
also there are different types of
authentication uh the important ones are
the basic uh you can use oauth 2.0 or
digest authentication uh ntlm and
Kerberos right so there are different
authentication mechanisms which can be
associated with every every API so you
can use any of this uh authentication if
it applies to your API okay you can also
send attachments you can also select a
security protocol if it is applicable
for your request okay
so now talking about this sample request
which I am trying to send so this is the
end point for this particular API
request and I'm going to mention it here
and after this uh we need to provide a
resource right now do keep in mind that
for every API request which you look at
it will always have this endpoint which
is common across all your API requests
and then there would be a resource which
is basically a unique location on the
server where you will be either
requesting information or you'll be
updating the information
so for me uh the resource is this
so whatever is mentioned here this is my
resource and this is what I want to do
okay
I want to get the information from this
particular resource
so for some reason I am not able to copy
this let's try it one more time
okay but okay let me type this in I
don't know why I'm not able to copy this
okay but let's type this in so slash API
slash users
and pH equals
two
okay so this is uh my resource and if
you look at this API page it doesn't
have any kind of authentication okay or
and also this doesn't require any kind
of parameter okay
so once I provide a endpoint and the
resource I can send this request and how
you can run a particular API message
request so there is a run option on the
top
so you can perform any kind of operation
on your API messages so when you're
sending a request you need to provide
the details and then you need to click
on run
okay once you click on run you will see
uh the tab which was on the request now
has changed to response okay because we
are looking uh at the response okay and
if you want to go back to your request
you can click back on this request if
you want to go back to a response you
can click it here it will show you a
status code now there are different
status codes so it will select whatever
it is getting from the response it will
show you the response time so you can
check how much time it took to process
this request and then the payload which
is the response API response which we
received from the server with all the
user details okay
so this is how you can simply uh send a
request and receive a response in your
Tosca API scan okay and you can create a
message you can create folders folder
structure for your API project and you
can then create any number of messages
and you can check all these messages
here okay
so this is the basic functionality of
Tosca API scan in the next video I am
going to show you
in the next video I am going to show you
how you can basically scan different
apis right from Tosca API scan and how
it will automatically create all these
messages with all the different values
and also a particular structure based on
your apis okay
so that's all for this video uh
hopefully this was interesting and do
tune in into our channel to watch the
next uh video on API testing where we'll
be looking at how you can scan different
apis and create your API project right
on the API scan application